In bearish midflow, what's the last inventory here?
Let me annotate.
Perfect, yeah?
So this whole area.
Yeah.
And if I grab it, what's the last inventory there?
Again, this area, yeah?
Yeah.
Now, in each instance, why is the inventory holding price down?
It's because the sell liquidity, so, you know, there was likely a large order, let's say 100 million.
It's plugged into an algorithm, or automate execution.
system which then fill this 100 million in small pieces over a distance of prices.
So, there's a huge 100 million here, sell liquidity, weak by liquidity, other traders who go
market order sell push price down, this liquidity chases and it holds here.
The same thing happens.
There's like 90 million left here, 10 million by liquidity here, market order sell, price
pushes down.
And again, the sell inventory, the bulk of the liquidity of this,
move is moving along with the price so whenever the midflow is strong we see a super consistent
behavior in bearish midflow which is what what is the characteristic um the well in this case
the cell bases always hold flow you you went off then i didn't hear what you said yeah i didn't hear
you either oh okay yeah so um the the cell bases will always hold um in bearish mid
flow.
Yeah, emberged midfall, yeah, these cell bases.
The reason I have an issue with your statement there is you said, cell bases will always
hold.
Well, yeah, always isn't exactly the right word because we have, yes, well, the last
session we've seen that they can do like deep tests and where sometimes technically it does
break, it can still go on for for a while.
Perfect.
So it's a misnomer.
We don't, you know, just to make sure we're using the right language.
Usually. Always, yeah, bearish midflow, at least a strong midflow, which this is reflecting a state of imbalance, yeah?
Whether it's heavier sell liquidity, weak by liquidity, then market orders and volume coming in cause price to go to less liquid side.
Right. So the strength is on the cell side, there's weakness on the buy side, it's a state of imbalance.
This is the visual characteristic. So the state of imbalance has to exist already. The cell liquidity has to be thick already.
and the bi-liquity has to be weak already.
Then when the volume comes in, the price will form.
You get it?
So the price is the visual representation of the imbalance.
And this is why we see this characteristic.
The cell bases hold, et cetera, et cetera.
So it's important that you connect with the characteristics of bearish midflow
with the state of liquidity, which is the imbalance, i.e., in bearish midflow,
we're seeing
thicker sell liquidity
stronger sell liquidity
and weaker by liquidity
which then results in
this type of pattern
but if that was the case
sorry I don't want to make it too complicated
but also on top of that
we know that these price moves out or drying off
which creates these areas
with this thinly traded
finally exhaust and prices to draw back up
to find sell liquidity
so we know why these characteristics are occurring
And finally, again, the way these large orders are filled, the transactional methods,
so if you can write this down, the transactional methods through which large orders are filled
or liquidity is delivered creates these midflow characteristics.
Because the sell equity is chasing price lower, it's holding price down like a wall.
Whenever the volume dries off, there's still that wall there.
Whenever the volume comes in, it pushes through the weaker side of the market.
And that consistently repeats until this 100%.
million is filled, filled, filled, fill until there's a very, very, very small amount left
in that inventory.
Do you get it?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
The inventory of sell liquidity is grabbed and filled and traded and filled and filled and filled
the further price travels until the last inventory hasn't got enough sell liquidity left
in there.
So let's just say there's only 3 million, right?
Typically, before prices, before the last inventory is so thin, we'll see a change in the
characteristics of mid-flow, what could that be?
One of these sole bases might get pushed through, so there's a break, yeah, there's a
break, and then then comes the parabolic phase where price stretches and usually gets
like super thin and, yeah, right, so parabolic, we'll come on to that, but if the visual
characteristics of strong imbalance are all the bases holding.
If and when the first base holds, it kind of shows you that the last inventory here was not strong
and that there's been a change in the momentum on strength on the cell liquidity.
So that's the first sign of the break of midflow, the break of the midflow characteristics
or the first sign of weakness.
And then typically price will stabilize and you'll get a quite an aggressive surge,
which basically the cell liquidity, the cell volume, sorry, is reaching for wherever they stick by
liquidity, all right? So now you have this area, which was drained. Think of it on the way down,
you had this $100 million. 10 was filled on the way down or 10 was filled there. Price ran down.
Price stabilizes. There's sell liquidity there. Market order buyers are coming through,
but they just can't push past the sell liquidity. In essence, the sell orders are getting filled here.
Yeah. Right. Price pushes down again, comes back up, picks up the liquidity or the sell liquidity
moves down here. Still, there's some market order buying going on, but it can't,
push through the cell liquidity. So on the way down, the cell orders are being fulfilled.
So on this whole way down, is this cell liquidity getting transferred?
It's classed. It's a misnomer. When I say misnomer, it's technically inaccurate or in, you know,
it's not the most accurate way to describe it. Liquity doesn't get transferred. Liquidity follows.
Okay. Right? It's a misnomer. So if I was to say to you that, I'll give you the definition,
right because I might just be a bit easier
a misnomer is a wrong or inaccurate name or designation
so it's inaccurate to say that liquidity is transferred
what the fuck's transferring it right
what we have is a dynamic where the cell orders have been split into small
pieces they filled over a distance of pips
and the algorithms which are delivering that liquidity
into the market are doing it in this way
where if price moves down the cell liquidity chases it
either aggressively or relatively
passively. Okay. All right
I might have called a liquidity transfer before
but over time,
little little things like that are corrected.
The price behaviour is the same
would just be in more accurate
with the way we're describing it.
Okay. So, you know, the parabolic phase,
you know, probably like around
here somewhere, is that when
whatever's left of the order
gets filled in like super aggressive?
Perfect. Not necessarily super aggressive, yeah.
So you have to differentiate between the sell liquidity, the sell limit orders, and the market order sells pushing price down.
Here you're having aggressive market order sales.
The sell liquidity has already been grabbed, grabbed.
There was a bit of weakness here because the sell equity has been picked and picked all the way down.
There's a bit of weakness here.
Like buying was able to push price through, the last inventory.
So already the weakness exists.
that's why price pushed through
the last sell inventory
now
there will
obviously
there will be some
sell liquidity here but not
significant
okay
so this is the inventory
the last base
that push price to new lows
or in bullish midfow
to new highs
is always the inventory
or the shelf
all right
okay
now by this point
price has been grabbed
grab grab grab grab grab
this area has now been
drained
here. So it's been picked, picked, picked, pushed out. What push price down here? Market order
sales. Market order sells. The sell limit order should really still be back here, no? Yeah.
Or if it was aggressive, the selling orders might hold price down here. But in other case, that
wasn't what happened. Market order bids were able to push price through the last inventory for the
first time. That's your first time. A week. Selling momentum has changed. And it's typically here.
you're going to see aggressive market order cells come through
to kind of maintain this phase of setting.
Simultaneously, it's not unusual
for there to have been small areas of bi-liquity
on the way down.
Yeah.
Right?
So these are all small areas of bi-liquity.
Not huge, huge amounts.
That's why it's the weaker side,
but there would still be some bi-liquidy.
But as a large order approaches,
so imagine we come to a level
where there's like a huge build-up of bi-liquity,
it wouldn't be unusual for this area
to show weakness.
So there'd be to be hardly any bi-liquity here,
but as you approach this level,
a huge build-up to present-to-present itself.
That's why Price kind of shoots through this area.
Yeah.
You get it?
What would happen if there was absolutely no bi-liquity on the way down?
How would Price sell off?
Very aggressive.
I would just go right through it, yeah?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
That's right through it.
Yeah.
In FX, you hardly ever see a candle,
and then the next candle open up here.
and then the next candle open up here
you actually have all the candles connected together
right in that sense
FX is again really quite liquid
all the volume is at least
you know the candles aren't separate
so when a market order buy comes through here
price doesn't have to jump to the next level to find sellers
it kind of finds it close to price
the market's quite thick in that sense
it's quite liquid
because the trade with the candles are representing
you know the market orders finding sell liquidity
is finding it in consistent streams
rather than in broken up amounts
if you look at stocks for example
they'll open up one day here
they'll open up the next day there
they'll have huge gaps in the middle
where absolutely no trade occurs
right
FX isn't the case so in that sense
FX is again broadly liquid
over a large enough time
it's liquid by any given instance
like here it can become quite illiquid
on the buy side
even if there's a candle going through it
on your screen, you can see a candle that sold off,
there was still market order cells that matched with bi-liquidy,
but just there wasn't enough bi-liquity there,
so price had to continue lower.
Are you following me?
But on the, you know, on the opposite end,
it's not like there's a consistent supply of bi-liquity either.
You could actually have 0.2 pip gap in between here
where there was no bi-liquity and price just jumped right through it.
the candle just fills that space, right?
The candle fills that space,
but in reality,
absolutely no transactions occurred there.
There was no bi-liquity in these two dots.
The next buy-liquity is there.
Price just jumped down two, three pips.
The candle fills it,
but still in, you know, technically no transactions occurred here.
So what we're seeing is this move of selling
or this wave of selling here
didn't actually facilitate a lot of selling, right?
Or at least a lot of sell transaction market orders.
were not matched with
by liquidity in quite an efficient way
because it was gaps in the middle. It actually broke
apart the way
the market traded here is not that
efficient in the scope of the
market, you know, trying to facilitate trade.
So
so like thinly, you follow me. Yeah, thinly dispersed.
Thinly dispersed and not linearly dispersed as well. You can actually
have gaps where there was actually no transactions traded
etc. or transactions formed.
Cool. So
the parabolic phase is
typically the most jumpiest phase of the price run so normally your candles even if this
gap lower like this year this inefficiency it started out here and the market order cell came
through and price jumped right past those two dots their next level and started trading here
for a minute but the candles on act they're actually forming quite slow price of the ticking
is quite slow right yeah whereas in the parabolic phase especially at the end of it it's
to be like this. Actually, it's like it's reaching for the buy liquidity. The market order
cells reaching for it, reaching for it, reaching for it, reaching for it. The market order buys,
sorry, the buy limit orders are kind of sucking down the market order cells. They're making them
jump for those levels there. It's typically as well, you know, because of this parabolic move,
you have such a thinly dispersed area of cell liquidity. There's not a huge buildup of market limit order
sell limit order sells so whenever the market order comes through price reaches right down and it
can come right back up on market order buying so at the thinest point in liquidity you'll usually
see price come to it come to it reach down and not spend too much time at the point of exhaustion
right the ticking the tick frequency the way price is forming is entirely different
whilst it's happening compared to most of the rest of the other candles especially during bearish midflot
so your ability to spot that is one that needs to be developed
when you look at a price chart a historical price chart
you won't see that difference because you're not seeing the candles form
all the candles have already formed you get it
but in lifetime when you start to track life prices
you will see a distinct difference in between the way
the parabolic leg forms and of course the preceding candles before that
now it's important at this stage here I introduce you to the idea of fractal
right we're talking about
fractal in a geometric sense.
So basically the definition of it would be
where there's patterns of self-similarity
on smaller scales.
The easiest example I could give you is a tree.
Yeah, you show me that tree with all the faces in, didn't you?
No, no, no.
That was just to show you a gay example
of seeing the less subtle details
from more obvious ones.
Trading is quite similar to that.
You do have less obvious per-priced
behaviors, and you have really, really obvious ones that you've seen that you can recognize quite
quickly. But in terms of fractal, the definition of fractal, it's patterns of self-similarity
repeating on multiple scales. So here you have a tree that's quite sheer, right? Here's a tree,
normally leaves form of these little shitty branches. And then this branch as well would have
this own leaf or small branch that would have its own branch
and then each of those smaller branches would have their own small branches as well
so the characteristics and the anatomy the shape of that small twig
with this smaller twigs there have the same structure as the overall tree
okay you get it yeah yeah the pattern in that smaller scale version
of that twig follows the same pattern of the broader the overall pattern
here the same way a leaf
show what we're talking about the same way
a fern tree
let me find you an example
it's important you capture it conceptually
because that's what price does
it doesn't matter what scale you look at price on
it has the same price swings whether it's one minute
all the way to like a daily chart
or a weekly chart monthly chart
so that's why sometimes I'm going to look at
three tick charts you want to what the fuck you're looking at
I'm just seeing the price is no different
on the three tick chart than it is on the weekly
chart the only difference is the
time taken to form the weekly charge is obviously
much, much longer.
These patterns of self-similarity,
the point in talking about this is
each of these,
what is that? And this.
And this.
In one sense of the world,
in the broader sense, it's an area
of thinly traded prices.
Right? So we can definitely agree
that's inefficient.
But that's
discussing the state of its liquidity,
how well the market facilitated.
trade what was you know what occurred with the market order sells and the limit orders
how the market traded there yeah on the other end that we're trying to that we're looking at
here is what condition is the market in broadly it's in bearish midflow yeah so here you have
a broader state of liquidity where prices in bearish midflow stronger sell liquidity and
and weaker by liquidity but then at times you're having these fractal smaller versions
of this price run
which are repeating
inside of that run
so what am I talking about here
you have a bearish midflow
the higher time frame
inside of it you still have areas
with selling's going on
but now down here
you literally have a condition
where there's hard any sell equity
the market order cells have dried off
and any light buying
is able to push price right back up
so now technically
wouldn't this be a state of bullish imbalance
wouldn't that be a smaller version
of bullish midflop
yeah it would at least for that short period of time yeah probably a lot on well depending on what time frame the the broader move is on probably like one minute five minute whatever inside of it yeah yeah so so just like the broader pattern here is bearish mid-flow cell bases hold the buy basis the lows don't hold and price overlaps past them to new lows etc etc the same condition or dynamic or visual characteristics are also present in this smaller move the characteristics are exactly the same just on a different scale
scale. There's a pattern of self
similarity. The characteristics
of bullish, of mid-flow are present
here in a bullish form, and
the characteristics of mid-flow are present there
in bearish form.
So this is the purpose and understanding
in fact. You're going to see
repeated characteristics
consistently across all
time frames that we can eventually try to
then it becomes a problem of how do we use all
this information, how we're going to navigate through it, etc.
This is why we, for
now at least, battening
down or like focusing on one condition of in markets which is midflow imbalance and then we are
going to transition into the apex where the reversals happen so right and then price goes to bullish midflow
and then it's going to exhaust then it's going to form a bearish apex with a buyers dry off and then bearish
midflow each of these are composed of the same patterns you have the phase where the market turns around
You have the phase where the market shifts into bullishment flow into the imbalance state,
where there's weak sell liquidity, stronger bi-liquity.
Here you have the point of exhaustion, the parabolic phase.
Here you have the, I guess, the reversal.
This is now showing you that the buy liquidity is now actually weak.
On the way up, the buy-liquity was super, super strong.
Now it's kind of confirming to you that the buy-liquity is weak.
This is called a shell flip, and then there's a shift in the state of liquidity.
So on the way up, there was thick bids, weak offers.
Yeah, and then on the way down, it's the other way around.
Yeah, so there's a shift in the state of liquidity,
by liquidity withdraws.
There's already an area which wasn't traded that thickly on the way up
and the same dynamic repeats on the way down.
So the whole point behind this is the split price up into small pieces,
at least the structure of which price moves,
which is the price swing,
break that down,
categorize it into different segments and stages
because each of them are different states of liquidity.
Right now we're just focusing on midflow slash parabolic phase.
But yeah, fractal is something that you need to kind of connect with and do your own validation
or go through your own process of validation and how it applies in charts.
So one simple version of that is, or a simple example of that is look at the daily chart,
you'll see some certain price behaviors, see if they're present on the one minute.
You can just go through your timeframes, inspect it, build your own level of understanding,
I guess, around it, just so you're not taking my word for it.
The validation, what do you call it?
The responsibility for you to validate anything I'm telling you is not mine, basically.
You have to do it yourself.
I will obviously tell you to do it and whatnot, but you get it.
So that's your responsibility to go through this in your own time, etc.
But where was we?
So that's fractal.
And yeah, what would be present in here then?
So here we had a market order cell.
there was weak by liquidity and prices selling off in that smaller leg what would that look
like if I was to look inside of it do you think um you'd see bearish midflow perfect exactly
100% you see bearishment flow even on a smaller scale here so again that's a function
that's an example of how there's self-repeating patterns on all scales fern tree
oh here we go again this is a bit gay but you just have to do things to make it
it seemed easy to understand.
All right, so here you have a firm tree.
Oh, my days.
Oh, God.
All right, go.
So here you have a firm tree.
You can see how there's a stem in the middle
and the multiple leaves coming off.
Each of the leaves shape is similar to actually
the overall fern leaf shape.
And then on a smaller scale,
each individual leaf also has a stem
going right through the middle with.
Again, smaller leaves coming off.
Yeah.
And then each of those smaller leaves of you
to go down to a, you know,
or more of a zoomed-in level,
you would see, again, a small, small stalk in the middle
with small lines coming off them at least,
which would eventually grow into leaves.
Now, the whole point of this is,
we're not discussing why this phenomenon of fractal exists.
You could argue that things grow towards a path of least resistance
and there's a whole kind of outside of trading point of study on this,
but that's not what we're doing.
All I'm doing is,
I'm making the observation that fact that exists even inside trading.
As a result of, you know, why does price form?
Why do we see candles forming going up and down?
They're just a simple result of liquidity dynamics.
How market orders, meet limit orders.
Of course, the limit orders can be dispersed.
They can be relatively thick.
And these create those price swings on all scales.
If you go down to the one minute, there's still all market orders coming through on the one minute chart.
Yeah.
Right.
actually that's not that's not that's not i'm probably being a bit inaccurate to say it like that
the one minute chart just shows you a zoomed in view of orders coming in over us uh you know
on a smaller scale basically so if i show you a chart uh if i shape this chart it's a five
minute chart we're seeing a much longer version that there were sell orders here and so
there was selling going on here with points of exhaustion by the way sell market order sales
dried off multiple times, multiple times, but we still saw consistent selling for this whole
period. And then again, we saw some consistent buying in this whole period. This covers a longer
timeframe, 13th of October to 60th, October, about two, three days. The same characteristics
are present. When I go down to the one minute chart, that doesn't change. All I'm just looking at
is the order is coming in
and how it affected
how we tried to find
liquidity on a much shorter scale.
Are you following me?
So the prices are always the same
and the characteristics are always the same.
The timeframe doesn't make any difference.
The only difference here will be
each candle will take
it will form quicker.
It will take much less of a while to form.
We typically see less liquidity
on these timeframes as well.
So the amount of liquidity
in this area that would build up
which is about a one-pip level
for a two-minute period
at maximum two-minute period
because the candle went away from it
within these two minutes
it wouldn't be that much
there wasn't a lot of trading that happened there
price didn't spend a long time there
actually it wouldn't have required a huge sell order
considered a move up into it
relatively thin price would have popped out
hit some sell liquidity the market orders dry off
left behind some weak bids
it wouldn't have taken a huge market order sell
to push price right back down.
Right? So not a lot of trading happened there either.
And the same kind of exists for every single candle
on the lower time frame.
When you compare it to a higher time frame
where in this, on this scale,
price spends a considerably longer time
in every single state location.
So down here, that's a whole 24 hours of volume
coming in trying to find liquidity there.
that's a whole 24 hours of volume coming in trying to find liquidity
much much more significant data in terms of reflecting
you know how much liquidity would be present in an area like that
it'd be much more okay right
a lot of trading is facilitated there for much longer time
so more liquidity builds up compared to a one minute chart
which where price only spends sometimes a matter of seconds
not a huge amount of liquidity gets to build up there
so that's the kind of point point again
Again, you know, in a different way of discussing it here is the longer the time frame,
the more liquidity turns up, the short of the time frame, the less chance liquidity gets to turn
up there.
And that's why you kind of see more volatility at least, or why price moves more and ticks more
on these lower timeframes.
Okay.
Whenever you're looking at a lower time frame chart, it can be ticking quite a bit.
Yeah.
But the visual characteristics of price, here you see there was definitely a sell order here,
a cell instance with sell liquidity chasing price.
down. We saw it, we saw it, we saw it, we
continue to see it. And then if I zoom into here, where you're going to see
is a break of bearish midflow. Price, this last candle,
where previously these candles on the way down, they would have just
formed and price stabilized. And then you would have had a small
sell off there, would have a small sell off here.
Do you get it? They're not that. They're not that.
A candle like this would have gone flash and right back up.
So flash, flash, right back up.
you could even do this and then flash and come right back up
but in other case the exhaustion points
on a fractal level
that's a smaller version of the exhaustion
just for this small price swing down and up
this might be the exhaustion point
of the bigger price swing down and possibly back up
I actually expect cable to gap higher today
probably open up somewhere here
and need to have a look at actually
we had a headline over the weekend
saying from the Brexit trade minister or something
that we're open to talks
and these are just playing a game honestly
Boris says that he doesn't want to
he's done talking and then the next day he wants to talk
and then what the hell
this has been going on
since I started trading four years ago
I'm not even trying shit to you bro
this is the exact same thing's been going on for for fucking four years
Brexit's been going on for four years
in 2016 now
is that when David Cameron was still in
yeah 2016 we voted
in 2017 we had a gap
but the market was worried
about the effects of it
in 2018
Theresa May started
to like set deadlines and shit
I think last year
no no at the end of 2018
yeah that's when she
Theresa May said yeah
there was that deadline set
and then there's a whole
there's been going on for years
I'm wrong by the way
cable's actually gaping down right now
it's at 2750
what
you're having a
fucking joke.
That much, 27.
No.
How's it got down that much?
Right.
It's right now, what,
2751?
It's here.
How's it got down that much?
Wait, something's happened.
Let me overlook.
That's serious, you know?
Can I show you?
Yeah, go on.
How do you even see where prices are right now?
It's because I'm a Saxo Bank client,
though.
Sure, 2750?
That's a massive move.
It's huge.
it actually hit the low at 2678 as well yeah i sent it to you on
shit man that's my other phone one minute let me get my one sucks with markets
yeah it's a big move i something that's happened i don't know what it would be you know
there was a terrorist attack in yeah that was franz in france yeah but that wouldn't that
wouldn't cause these kind of responses in the market b oec's economic risk skewed very heavily to
downside. There you go. The Bank of England Governor, Bailey, the fat bastard, he's going to go negative
interest rates. I said this in December 2019. Actually, no, no, I don't think I remember that tweet.
No. I said it multiple times. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I didn't see it in 2017. He said today, I think about
3pm that the country faces on. He's basically taken a tone which says the central bank's view on the
economy for the short term is that the economy is not going to recover as heavily skewed to it
outside and that means lower interest rates that's why pounds all over anything interest rate interest rate
related is always going to be like that fuck off that's a big move for the weekend but it doesn't
actually have to stay there it could gap it could come back up and fill it up so so what happens you
know over the weekend so when price gaps down
isn't that technically very very inefficient so if price gaps down to like 2750 that means
the look we the prices we get that from that are streaming from our brokers the banks
actually before the market opens on 10 p.m. on Sunday they're already quoting already
so they've started to set quotes for each other they're going to be you know if there's any
transactions waiting from over the weekend they can start filling them now or if a bank had to
they can trade between themselves if they have some risk they want to offload
etc etc they can start setting their bid and ask quotes based off the pre-market volume coming
in okay but we as retail we are not the primary clients in the market right so their clients
they might have had orders over weird for the weekend since the weekend but let's just say
there was a set order from their clients over the weekend the first price that is a bidder
that the bank can find is down at 2751 that's where the order is
getting filled you get it yeah and that's where the price to start trading so that's where the
price forms there's the highest bidder there's a market order cell that comes through that's where
the price starts that's why you typically see banks they don't want to hold on to risk longer than
about 18 minutes that's a mad gap there you go that's a daily chart oh i can't can't see anything
it's on your what's up oh okay so do you get it yeah so like if the the market dries up
there's hardly there's no volume over the weekend two
three hours before the market
opens, a market order
sell comes through and this is where the buy
liquidity is, that's exactly where
the market's going to go down to.
And then the sell equity might be there.
The next market order that comes through goes right
directly up there and price starts doing
this before the week opens.
That's why there's such a big move.
The market's so illiquid right now.
No, that's a huge move looking on the daily.
Yeah. It's just gone right
back down to retest this daily apex.
Like I said, that's
where you would expect.
by liquidity. Can you see my scream?
Yeah.
It's gone down and retested that.
I thought it'd be going back up.
Pounds shit, man.
It's going to 150.
I'll put any money on with anybody.
The pound is going to 150.
So it's going to pass tail.
Or to that line, basically.
That'd be nice.
When it does, I don't know.
Look, this could quite easily
work here
and then by mid-2020
jump out
it could
sell off here
on some super bad Brexit news
stabilise
and then start moving out
as the market relay
because my bet is always going to be
at the moment in time at least
the UK will benefit from Brexit
the GBUSD
will benefit from leaving the European Union
the sentiment around EU in my opinion
again in the next five 10 years
it's going to continue to depreciate
so the better trade
would be to short EuroGDP
but these are swing trades
based on macro
not even macro just based on like
sentiment ideas that I'd have
not the way I trade
because we don't at my opinion
trading directionally requires you to be right
about a big thing
you have to be right that is strength
in the market willing to buy
relatively aggressively an asset
for a long period of time
yeah whereas it's much better
just to be right for a few minutes,
whatever, whatever, get your arm.
No, no.
Trading at the exhaustion point,
you only have to be right about that
a very short period of time.
And then once prices away from your entry point,
you can give it a chance.
You can try to hope for sell strump to come in
and push it lower.
But at the point of entry,
I need it to be skewed liquidity
to increase the probability
of the initial manageable response.
Right?
So you can look for big trades,
do a hit rate on them,
sorry, the frequency of big trades
will be quite low.
You won't really get them that often
in a pair like GbP, U.S.D or any major peer.
So U.S.S.S. French, GbP U.S.D, you're U.S.D.
You can get them an Australian dollar,
New Zealand dollar, because they're risk currencies.
But if you want those like big swing trades,
you're looking at peers like GbPJPY
or AUDJPY, even GBP New Zealand dollar.
Those assets will rally like,
motherfuckers. Not ready, but they will just trend like motherfuckers. I don't like that because I like to be
quite active in and out of the market, taking advantage of the price behavior rather than making
their directional bias. If I'm trading in a certain direction based on some form of existence,
you know, some existing bias, I have to be right about it. Whereas trading at point of exhaustion,
I can be totally wrong about the broader market direction. So price is bullish here, but I can short this
and capture profit. Because at that point,
point, it's impossible for pricing continue.
The bids are thin, et cetera, et cetera.
So trading the volatility, which is created as a result of the liquidity dynamics discussed,
this actual edge in there, that doesn't go to mean, though.
It's not saying you can't be a directional trading.
You can.
It's about, because what's going to happen is you're going to, when you start exercising
and you start trying to, like, just build your ability, you're going to experience times where
the market's super stable.
There's many times where it's directionally driven.
each of those environments have various characteristics.
You might connect with the characteristics of the directionally driven environment
where you'd recognize it quite well or you at least have the willingness to buy
at more expensive prices and ride that wave.
So you'd essentially be a similar, you know, akin to a trader who's more of a breakout trader.
It doesn't mean you'll buy breakouts really nearly in the middle of nowhere.
You'll have specific entry strategies which increase your probabilities,
but still it'd be a slightly different type of trading
than me who likes to push price back into range.
You get it?
The reason I trade this way and I trade GDP-USD
because it's a peer that ranges predominantly most of the time, right?
So it makes sense for my trading style
to trade an asset which fits that style.
That is I'm going to say that I don't trade mid-flows.
I do, but just don't have much lower,
you know, there's a much lower frequency of trades in that environment.
and I'm much less aggressive.
I give my trades much less of a chance.
I know that I'm going to take losses in this environment
because of the way I trade.
It doesn't mean I'm not trading at all.
It's just about recognizing which environment.
So the point here is you can be a breakout trader.
You will learn the characteristics of types of environments
where it's heavily, directionally driven,
and you may connect with them where you can take advantage of them.
You'll have specific trade plans and entry parameters
all of that shit will be internalized
is just a case of
before you know that you have to experience everything
you get it
I wouldn't worry too much about it
but anyway
that's that
so let's just move on to
what did I just close there
you're a GPP in it
yeah
if you said to me you're a trend trader
I would send you directly to these assets here
SAB 500 Dow Jones 30
when you have a slightly bigger account
NASDAQ is also
these are the trending markets
you're still see in inventory here
you know buy basis hold
price breaks the last buy base
there pops and starts to draw back in
but these go into midflow
on the higher time frame
they last for a very long time
they're much less balanced
than the state of liquidity
in FX we have demand for buy liquidity
for pound and buy liquidity for the US dollar
it's a different type of market
in equities
they're directionally driven
there's a sentiment based
rally I guess
you can you can just tell
just by looking at it
yeah for for much longer periods of time
buyers come in at higher and higher prices
without drying off
well that's technically again
a misnomer buyers do dry off
but the buy liquidity is there present
do you get it
then the buy what sorry drops
the buyers do dry off
because not the buyers are dry enough.
The market water buyers are dry enough time and time again.
But the buy liquidity is continuing to accept higher prices for really long periods of time.
That's like a two-year rally.
That's 518 days, but you only have five trading days a week.
Do you get it?
This is 518 trading days.
It's not included in the weeks.
So that is more than a two-year period.
For a whole two years, we saw buy liquidity.
except higher and higher prices.
Just think about what that means.
Any shorts you would have taken,
you have to be short term,
all the buy bases are holding.
So you could only really trade this well
if you're a directionally trend trader
or you can trade with the flow.
Here's midflow.
You can trade counterflow against it
or you can trade with the flow with it.
Both will have unique entry parameters.
Both will have different types of midflows
which are favorable and not favorable.
So this
You can actually trade with the flow and against the flow
Because you're getting responses on both sides of the market
Here, in this bullish midflow
It's much more directionally driven
By bases are even higher and higher
They're not breaking
Here you can't really short this
You follow me
Yeah, the only thing you can do in this situation
Is be long from the bottom
That's it
Be long from the bottom
Depending on the time
So if this is a daily char
Right
You could
You could buy these
because price is fractal
that move down
would be like a small
bearish price swing
so let's just do this
I'm going to
zoom into this area
pretend zoom in
in this circle
in red
so we're going to start
from the high to the low
so here's that high
parabolic phase
shifting state of liquidity
price goes into bearish midflow
and then it builds up here
you see that area
likely broke a shelf
here's your sideways here's your pop
you might be taking a view that
this small price swing
which is just that move down
is likely to meet
a huge area of buy liquidity
because of the higher
time frame state of midflow
and you could easily turn to a buyer
here trying to ride it higher
you can't do if the midflow is higher
higher time frame enough
this bullish midflow is relatively
inefficient it's not like this
then you could do absolutely nothing
if the daily chart looks like that
then yeah you can fucking do shit all
both so yeah we're going to discuss this
in a lot of depth anyway
let's move on
I wanted to really talk about
internalisation notes
just give me one moment please
so yeah
internalization we discussed
the touch on it last session
the whole purpose of it is
as you go through
prices what we already discussed today
is that there's various different types of environments
you're going to have to experience them all
to have an implication on the way you can trade them
etc
over time have to build
at least a relationship with price
behaviours
you need to understand why they exist conceptually
so how they why they happen
you then need to understand how they are visually
present in charts
and connect those two together so understand the concept
and connect it together and tie it together with
obviously the visual
we're already doing that in the form of
price swing
we're looking at you know
in the in the price swing when it's forming
we have
a move up and I move down.
It's split into pieces.
You have your midflow,
you have your sideways pop,
which is the breaking midflow pop.
It doesn't always have to break midflow,
but it will typically be a sideways pop.
Here you have your shelf absorption slash flip,
shift in the state of liquidity,
and into bearish midflow.
So broadly speaking, there's like three main stages,
midflow, apex, and the reversal.
Any individual swing
So this is composed of
Oh shit
That's composed of
A price swing
Is composed of two price runs
A to B
And then B back to A
Yeah that's one price run
Open that back down
No
That is a price swing
Oh that's price swing
A swing is composed of two
Individual price runs
Okay
The A to B
And then B back to A
they're two runs okay
you get it
each of the runs has an apex
a mid-flow
a break and pop
and then the
the second run we also have an apex
a shell flip
a shell flip a mid-flow
a break and pop
etc etc
everyone so here you have a full price swing
from A to B
and then B back to A
yeah
this has a high
this was the last inventory
that pushed it to new highs
Price then flipped the shelf
shift in the state of liquidity
bearish midflow
broke midflow down here
flipped the shelf
went into more of an efficient
bullish midflow
broke midflow around here
popped
and now I was doing the same kind of thing
yeah
do you get it
now just because
it's important that I tell you
quite early on
just because prices
let's just say
showing the characteristics of a reversal
and it's highly likely
that price will shift out into bullish midflow
doesn't mean it always will.
The problem with realizing that,
so when you're looking at historically examples,
all of them flipped into bullish midflow
they flipped the shelf
and they went into bullish midflow,
all of them look successful
because the historical price swings you're looking at
were the successful ones.
But at any given point,
price can start to show characteristics
of a price feature or a price swing stage
and then that price swing stage failed
so here this could have been
a break of the last inventory
price coming back up to retest
the high basically
yeah moving back down yeah
it could have flipped the shelf
and gone into bearish midflow
it could have it was entirely possible
in fact it could have been quite probable
but it did not happen
right so the outcome
the probability in the outcome
are always separate as we've discussed
the probability of an outcome
might be 99 to 1
but the next
outcome under these probabilities
could easily be the losing one
so each individual outcome
does not necessarily reflect the
probability it's only over a large
sample over many
many many many times
you will see that this reflects
99 to 1
not individually
so it's like you know if I flip a
coin 50 heads heads or if a paper coin the heads could come up and I flip it again heads could
come up this is showing 100% heads yeah even though the probability is 5050 it doesn't
reflect the probability does it yeah yeah it needs a much larger sample we need to flip the coin
many many more times for it to eventually show 50 50 heads and tails that's called a law of
large numbers probability is only show up over a large of a large sample so over time
you're going to be exposed to this problem you can be identifying price features and price
behaviors that have discussed with you some of them won't work some of them will work
and then from that junction it's going to be a case of trying to identify the ones that do not work
and cutting them trying to identify the ones that are working and holding them that's the management
side of things okay so it's much much more difficult than what it seems at this moment in time
it seems as if we can all spot these price swings and we can all trade them but in a live
environment when prices are forming is dynamic probabilities can change instantaneously so where one thing
was a highly you know it was highly likely that price would do one thing in the next minute that can become
completely invalid yeah and we have to have an approach which is open to that we have to you know be quite open to
so having and building a relationship with price behaviors is one where you initially understand them
conceptually and you understand why prices form and how they form why the price behaviors exist what
you need in trading, which is an edge, etc.
And then get an intimate with them via process.
So by getting intimate, I mean directly engaging them,
building a process to navigate through, you know,
to building a process to exploit them.
If you consistently see price fields and efficiencies,
that doesn't mean you can now trade price inefficiencies.
The difference between the one who can trade the inefficiency and the one who knows
they exist is the one who can trade it knows how and when to time the trade.
how to manage the trade
when to cut it if it's not
working out whereas the one who
just knows that the inefficiencies get filled
if he tries to trade it
he'll short it there short it there
short it there short it there short it there and continue
to short it and then when the trades are losing one
he'll continue to hold that loser without ever closing it
that's the difference between skill
and execution
versus the opposite end
which is just understanding
both are critical
you start with your understanding and you build the skill
right
ignore my arrows and shit because it's so retarded
if someone ever saw this they think I'm a fucking idiot
I can't speak to you
and simultaneously come up with a nice drawing
to make you look yeah but
we don't need the drawing anyway
the skill is what we build
through the getting into my process and exercising
so through this process you will form a unique
understanding of market trading price
relative to your own personal psychology or you know psyche
this is where that that point i've been discussing today with you comes in
you might be the guy that trades this bang bang bang bang you clear a million
or you might be the guy that trades this and again you clear a million over time
it just depends on who you are as a person or what kind of trading fits your mental
your psyche i will help you discover that as well
based on like the times of exercise you take and whatnot but at this point in time
Again, the point is that you understand how and why we're doing what we're doing.
You can get intimate with a process at least.
So the unique understanding of you form is one where you've seen price behaviors occur over and over and over again.
You know they exist and they're true.
You've also built your ability to exploit them through using fractal and using the tools that we're discussing.
One of the tools is price swing.
That's why we're breaking the tools down for different users.
In bullish midflow, we use fractal for something.
in the apex stage we're using inefficiencies
or even in bullish midflow
if I'm trying to trade against the midflow
I'm trying to short this inefficiency
or this inefficiency.
Do you get it?
So we're using each of these behaviors
and the tools to navigate price and trade it.
You will be using them to exploit the behaviors
you've seen with that work over and over and over
to an extent where it's only you
that understands on an extremely unique level
how to trade that particular
price behavior.
It's so unique that if you were to write
out your exact rules for somebody else,
the exact rules you follow,
how to manage the trade, take the trade,
the rules for entry,
if you wrote them out for somebody else
and then you went to, you know,
one on one against each other,
trying to trade your strategy,
you would always come out with the better results
because you know things about that setup
that can't be taught, right?
Small, small subtle differences
that you've seen happen over a very large sample.
I'm talking tens of thousands of examples
of that one specific behavior
that you engage and build trading around,
it just results in you having a much,
much more of an informational skill-based,
intuitive edge as well.
So it's critical that any trader that wants to trade
goes through this process of building a unique understanding,
see the market in a way that's unique.
You're validating price behavior initially,
that's what we're doing right now,
while it's developing a niche in specific areas.
By niche, I mean you specialize in one area.
It might be in efficiencies.
It might be trading with the flow.
It might be trading in higher time frame and efficiencies.
The niche can be quite broad,
but it will specialize in one specific type of trading
before you can identify what your niche is.
You have to try all types of trading.
One example would be try taking retests.
Don't take the first touch, try to take the retest trade.
See how that works.
Try taking the first touch trade.
where you only go first touch of a level
over time you'll find out
when the retest trades work
when the first touch trades like to work
what the probabilities of each different type of entry is
we'll also discuss
or you'll also go through the motions
of trading a highly highly
an efficient bullish midflow
and trying to buy it
why you can't buy it
you'll also go through the dynamics of trading
a much more efficient bearish midflow
and how it feels to trade that
over time you will specialize
in one type of environment,
not necessarily just want to have
like either efficient or inefficient environment.
There's obviously shades and differences between them.
Yeah, so that can become your niche.
So everything from trade entry to trade management,
trade selection, all of that combined together
results in like a skilled interface
when you're interacting with the market.
Once these concepts have been validated
and the price behavior as well
that's connected to the conceptual side of things
has been validated and understood,
nobody else
you can take trades
first touch off levels
with a three pip stop
take out nine pips from it
because you just bored
you want to fuck off on the screen yeah
you capture three or nine pips
and if anybody else looks at you
like what the fuck are you trading how are you trying to catch knives
or what you don't require anybody else's validation
you know that that person
has not done the same work as you
they don't even understand price on the same level as you
not because you're better than them
it's just the case of like we see the market
through a different lens.
We're looking at the market
through Chanel tents basically.
It gives you access to
a type of trading, which is more appropriate
for financial markets as they exist today.
The more appropriate for retail trade is trying to
exploit and exploit
edges when edges have been
dying, basically. There is
no edge in trading breakouts. There is no
edge in trading late. Hardly any
edge in trading retest. You get like one or two
good trades a fucking weak, bro.
People might take retest trades on a five
minute chart on mt4 and show you their lines that they showed the trade one but what you can do
on mt4 is you can cancel the lines of you're losing trades retest trades are in say again i didn't know you
could do that i'm sure you can like right click what you know the lines that people show yeah yeah
i'm sure you can right click that line and like hide it yeah you probably can um but yeah so
there's a multitude of levels difference between just having a basic approach which is not really
appropriate for trading and one that is the difference will be you as a person and your
interactions with the market the tools are what we're using yeah yeah the tools are price swing
the tools of the price behaviors they were trying to exploit fractal becomes a tool um but it's all
about like yeah it's about using them so the things you can look forward to being able to to
recognize and be able to have solutions for or as follows but just remember that yeah so
validated and understood and skill is basically the junction where you don't need validation
from everybody else because you've done the work on your part you're an independently thinking
trader everything that you do in the market you don't you know how many traders look for validation
externally why are men on twitter loads they look for it's filled the ego isn't it no i i wouldn't
even say ego if i'm honest with you i would say they do not have the necessary conviction
and their own ability
or whatever they're seeing in charts
they want to share
their ideas of everyone
and when you're in something like
what's that guy
you know offshore keys
everybody's thinking the same way
so there isn't anybody criticising
anybody else's idea
it's just all looking at the same thing
and basically bomb-licking everyone's ass
that again isn't really a true reflection
or it doesn't really
whatever results they show to each other
is all kind of showy showy
but they don't ever get to test
how valid their approaches in the markets
you get it
because on an individual level
they're not showing the full results
on an individual level I would argue
that their trading does not work
they get fucked over by market
the volatility changes
as soon as the market
I know they get fucked over
but when you're in a group of like 20 other people
or 50 or 100 over people
showing you the winning results selectively
showing you the strategy works
you then have to you want to then conform
and also only show you winners
now separate yourself
from that group that group is now
like an online fucking
forum which is only showing
you winning trade only showing you
examples of the trade strategy working and
kind of tricking people into thinking it actually
works
it becomes self-fulfilling
that isn't a true reflection on the validity
of this style of trading
they then require everybody else's validation
because on a personal level the trade doesn't work
in the group it does work so they look
for everybody else's validation.
They are not independent thinking traders.
You come over to this
Chanel-in view, right?
Everything you will do is your own validation.
I will tell you every single time
your trade is shit.
It couldn't matter to you.
So again, independent thinking,
as a trader at least,
is a critical part.
Specific price behaviors are learned simultaneously
on such a level that you will
you basically nobody else can copy them right now some of the things like I said you can look forward
to knowing is timing you first need to understand the parameters the rules basically the things that
you look for around a specific trading model what is trying to achieve or what you're engaging
to do that to time your trades first of all you have to validate once you validate you have to try
to use tools to try to exploit these price behaviors one of them is timing the entry of the trade
miss through experience.
We're going to discuss various different types of entry
types, for example.
Already I've given you to retest or first touch.
But before that, you also have to learn how to draw levels.
Now, each time you interact with a particular price behavior,
you form an experience.
The more structured your interactions are,
i.e., the more information that you've retracted
about the context, about that particular trade,
the more accurate your experience outcome will be.
be. If you just looked at something superficially and said, yeah, this is going up, yeah, it's
an efficient, so I'm going to buy it. And you're doing very, very simplistic, low-level type
focus, low-level type of analytical approach, you know, if there's a low-level focus on it,
your results won't necessarily be that accurate. So it will be difficult when you're engaged
and you're always going to be wrong and it's requiring you to focus quite deeply. But over time,
you're building comfort you're building comfort by shifting your psychological viewpoint on what the
market can do where it's best to trade it'll be entirely different basically where you deeply
believe it's best to trade compared to everybody else everybody and everybody else would
always tell you or majority of people tell you that you should trade after a confirmation
yeah based on the behaviors I've seen it's impossible for me to believe that I can
break the confirmations down, by the way.
So, yeah, you'll shift your psychological viewpoint
in the market by making adjustments
to the new scenarios that you've seen playing out
what's possible in the ways they can play out.
They'll play out in ways you didn't anticipate in the past.
In the past, you would have ignored the small details
that, you know, the differences between one is a losers
and the differences between big trades and small trades.
Here, because, first of all, like,
people don't have the necessary language or framework
to see the sort of difference.
If I didn't discuss with you fractal, it would have always been like this conflicting scales.
Sometimes it's going up, but now we've defined what fractal is.
Based on that, we can come up with a rule for separating small swings from big swings.
And we know also now that each swing has the full price swing features.
If it's a price swing on a one minute, it has a one minute midflow apex, sideways,
pop, reversal.
If it's a weekly price swing.
swing it has a weakly midflow
did you get it?
Every swing has price features
because price is fractal.
The price features are made up of the way
orders are dealt in the market and the
liquidity dynamics.
The liquidity dynamics are present on every single
scale. So every single price
swing has all the full features.
Now again
you will shift your
viewpoint, you'll
build into your experience
various types of scenarios
that you didn't expect before
how they can play out
you'll also realize
the dynamics of random distribution
of probability and outcome
just because you've taken a trade
for a specific behavior
so you know you've seen a certain behavior
work over and over and over again
just because you're trying to trade it
the next time you will realize
there is times where it just simply is not going to work
and in that process
there's ways to like identify the losers
from the winners because the price will reflect the weakness in your trade.
So over time, an appropriate psyche shift takes place
where you never have strong, rigid expectations or biases.
Really, it's just a consequent, constant,
it's always constantly unrealised probabilities
for what price should do alongside an appreciation for price behaviours
or like outcomes that are less favourable
you're just thinking in a way that's appropriate for the markets
you approach it in a way that's appropriate for the markets
that is going to that essentially reduces the stress you get from markets
I actually don't stress about losing trades
I get pissed off but I don't stress there's a slight difference there
if I lose two free trades in a row I'm pissed but I'm fucking pissed
but the stress of me taking an entry and worrying about it losing
it's just not present I'm aware that I'm going to lose and you get it
So there is, again, an actual shift in your psyche
and how you view the market on a multi-faceted level,
on multiple scales.
There's dimensions to that shit.
I don't mean to make it sound like you're going to become a superhuman.
You're not.
We're just talking about subtle but significant changes
in the way you see if you approach the market,
which give you a wider access to trading in different ways
in exploiting edge.
We're looking for edge.
This is the point.
Also, you'll have mental.
reference points for winners and losers how they develop you'll realize outcome is random and then
we need the solutions for this the process to interact the price should be done thousands and thousands
of times over the next two three years that doesn't mean you won't be trading live within two years
I still interact with like tomorrow when the market opens I'm not going to take my first the first
I'm not going to take my first trade basically I'm going to go back into the process of tracking price
through exercising and through tracking it basically
by engaging it
a few dozen times
until I'm thinking properly
until I'm identifying the right information and know what that
feels like I have my
to get it and then I'll be looking for my trades
this is why it's quite important to wake up quite earlier
at that
and just like we've discussed your brain
identifies the nature of the moves that are
favorable the nature of the moves that are less
favorable
yeah
so it's critical
so some of the things you can you know
you want to look forward to in the future for how we're going to use them or what you need to
identify is premise for trade selection, the level selection, the price behaviors into your
levels, the types of entries, how you're going to manage the trade, what the winners look like,
users look like, how we're going to use fractal, the lower timeframes to select time,
what information can be retract from fractal.
Liquidity base, there's different types of liquidity bases, you have shelf or inventory,
which is the same thing, you have different types of bases as well.
the level of volatility in the market
how inefficient is it
what time frame is the inefficiency
the current prices
the best bid best offer
how are you going to actually take your entry
sorry for the current prices
are you going to go market order sell on the bid
or are you going to put sell limit orders there
yeah
so some of these things
what are mainly your
your executions on
are yours usually like limits or market orders
yeah I'll be honest with you
it used to be limits on
I see markets, I now struggle to get filled with limit orders.
Oh, on the Saxo Bank.
Yeah.
So I will, it's a balance.
Right now it's a balance, but I prefer limit orders because you have the risk of positive
slippage.
Negative slippage is impossible.
Yeah, yeah.
There are times you have to use market orders because prices is very unlikely to reach
your level.
But again, how do I know when it's unlikely to reach my level?
It's through consistently, and many, many times experiencing the conditions in which
how price looks in the times it misses my level it won't reach there what's happening in those
environments honestly there's such a high level of combinations of possible outcomes and like
contexts i'll give you one example you can have inefficient with a with a broke midflow
price run that's in the sideways pop stage these are all looking good for sure and no yeah so price
broke mid-flow, some sideways path, it's inefficient at the highs, but there's no, there's, there's
hardly any shit level, there's a shit level there. How do I define my risk? Now, think about,
as we go through the motions, price could be in multiple different locations. It could be embellished
mid-flow, it could be an apex, it could be in shell flip, it could be in bearish, but I guess that's
the same. So it could be in shell flip, it could be in the apex, it could, within the apex, there's
like apex retest, and there's a few other locations in some.
the apex.
Apex is the highs and the lows.
Right.
You have inefficient, efficient,
and there's a whole spectrum of middle ground between them.
And yeah, so there's not only this,
but there's also a timeframe.
You can have different timeframes
of bearish midflow,
abolish midflow.
Price can be inside of higher timeframe, efficient areas,
higher time frame, inefficient areas.
All of these can have, you know,
a huge amount of different combinations.
that you need to experience
and this is even all of it
there's event-driven environments
where there's a new event
with the harding liquidity in the market
the time of day
will start tomorrow
the time of the month
so like if there's
interest rate decision
there's a huge
huge amount of experiences
that you have to build up
for all these particular combinations
or any individual combinations
which will take years
100% it will take years
how do you know when the next combination
that you're looking for will turn up?
You know, you just have to wait for it to happen
and you to build, you know, as price unfolds,
it will do many, many different things
or go into many different environments,
there'll be various different influences on the market.
There'll be changes in narratives and sentiment,
all of these things collectively over time,
you consistently experience with them,
always being present to experience them.
This is, and having the appropriate framework
to, you know, to understand
price approach it, trade it, build the process of it.
It's only through that you result, that you eventually get to that level of niche
skill, exploiting behaviours that you understand where you have an appropriate process for
markets, etc.
Only then.
Yeah, you have to keep getting exposed to it, don't you?
Yeah.
That's what it is.
And it's not impossible, but the problem, the problem arises when someone starts to try
and make money because they've had a few areas of success, the market environment was great
for them. As the market environment changes, if you try to start making your money here,
you'll start ingraining things in your process, which are the wrong thing. And simultaneously,
your focus becomes on trying to actually build money rather than still observing price like a student
of the market. So that's typically one of the main reasons people take a long time to learn.
They consistently going back and forth for trying to make money, then realizing the need to be
learners and do that each. If you just stick to this initial 60,
to eight to nine months of hitting the market
and very, very hard without any money,
just observing these behaviours,
you'll quickly, quickly build your skill.
But realistically, the process of exercising
and like not being a full-time trader
should take you about two years, 24 months.
Okay.
And that probably means hitting the charts
for an average of six to eight hours a day,
if not more, for 24 months
and you're making,
and you're only building small accounts
yeah so
this is how I see it
I don't benefit of you
learning for a longer period by the way
it's not like I'm the charge you for 24 months
after this eight weeks I don't benefit from you at all
but I would still always say
you shouldn't trade live
so this is not because
it's not like ICT where you sign up to his mentorship
and he benefits from like longer and shit out for you
I don't
There's actually reasons for this.
The way your brain learns, the types of different environments to save you from trying to
make money and just losing focus, reversing your progress, you, again, like if I had to
explain it to you how progress works, it's simply defined as nonlinear.
So here's your level of progress, yeah?
Zero to a multimillionaire type trader level of ability.
And then here's time.
just because you put in one week, two weeks, three weeks, four weeks of doing the same effort
of exercising doesn't mean you've had the equivalent rise of four weeks worth of progress.
Actually, there's likely going to be a latent effect where you will put in weeks and weeks
and weeks and weeks and weeks a worth of effort and then it could only take one week and you start to do that.
Right? So you had one week here.
hardly any effect. Another week here, hardly any effect. Another week, hardly in effect. Another week, hardly in effect. But the fifth week, you had all the other week's worth of effects come in and present itself. And it's obviously not like that. It will still be steady growth. It actually turns into this. You have growth. You hit a wall where you're fucking up. And it's something you need to solve in your trading. You build a salute. You identify the problem. You build a solution for it. And then you move on to the next hurdle.
And most of your time, it seems as if you're spending it in the same area.
But only small improvements.
But over time, they build up.
This is how the progress of learning occurs.
So most of the time, you'll spend in problem phases and not in, like, where you feel like you're doing amazing.
Okay.
That's where you're, think about how, what the implication of that is on your motivation to continue learning.
If most of the time you feel like you don't know shit or like you've just solved a novel problem,
you've got another problem now.
You don't know how all these things fit together.
It's like operating in the darkness.
You never have a view of the full picture until you do.
Right.
This is where it requires, obviously, motivation and desire to win and be hungry and whatnot.
I'm not a motivational speaker.
I'm just trying to show you early on that most of what you will do in trading,
even when you're making money, is always adversity.
It's always adversity.
You are always operating an uncertainty, not knowing the future, not knowing the full picture.
are when you're taking a trade,
when you're trying to learn price behaviours
that there's so many different variations of,
then you have to add the element of human error
and thinking, you know, like our brains getting inflated
and our ego is being inflated sometimes
because we've had like two free, good, you know, did you get it?
Yeah.
So yeah.
If you can write through that,
you're having a decent chance
of being able to take two, three losses in a row,
not being your fault from the market
is trying to behave in a wrong way
and you're surviving that day.
the best way I can describe it to you
is taking a day to day basis
fuck where you're going to be in two years
just focus on right now
yeah
yeah it's perfect mindset
it's more appropriate man
if I can show you
what you can expect
when you're learning
at least then
once you start to experience this shit
you might have forgot what I told you
but eventually you'll remember
how this guy said
it's going to be like this
you will be losing
a majority of your exercise
You will operate, initially when you're starting out, your reference point of understanding
about what's possible, where this edge, where there's not, is here.
The more you feed experiences into here, structured experiences, then it gets bigger and bigger and bigger
until you know a huge, vast amount of information and skill as well.
But what do I mean by structured experiences?
Well, you could experience and engage the market thinking,
heavily manipulated that you could you could view it through false and against false principles
whatever information you get from that then is likely not going to be that worthwhile or true
feed those experiences off that false you know let's say seeing the market through like a false
prism whatever experiences you get from that shit if you feed that into your psyche then
you're just creating and like you're not actually you're not developing basically
yeah it's like um it's like um it's like um iCT style how you know there's a a stop hunt usually
there's another stop hunt and then when you ask someone why did this happen it's oh i just wanted
to take your money again but like why why did it happen why why the other time why did it not
happen then why did they not want to do it yesterday and i wanted to do it today that oh you just
just like that yeah i agree they're trying to give randomness a fucking uh i
a universal explanation, which is very
simplistic, but
not because I'm better than them.
I'm never saying that. The point is
they're too
ignorant to
realize that this requires a huge
amount of effort.
They've never reached that phase of learning
where you can expect
basically like we've just
discussed, when you are going through the motions
of like building intuition and learning, whatever,
that progress curve
is not linear and it's heavily
heavily involves
adversity, yeah?
It's inherent.
Because of the adversity
that is present there,
people kind of back away from it.
And then they want to oversimplify
and find other routes which are easier.
They're taking the back door.
They're taking the easy route.
And then they're going to share that false information
wherever everybody else
where they don't actually understand shit.
Yeah, they don't understand.
I have a problem with that.
I don't have a problem with the individual
not being a taught.
Did you get it?
Like, I'm not better than them.
But if you want to be,
operating in something that is random outcome
you never know the future
and you're trying to predict the future basically
in a consistent basis
and then you tell a man to fucking simplify it
come up with these false narratives
you're an idiot bro
you actually deserve to lose all your money
not because everybody else is better
none of that shit I'm not superior to anyone
I'm just saying you're a fucking idiot
there is typically a dynamic
where people oversimplified things
because they refuse to be either they have no capacity to like think critically about something
or learn about it but they refuse the adversity of learning that's my i would always simplify
it i'm kind of simplified right now as well but which is a hypocritical but yeah they're avoiding
that adversity that's inherent to learn it yeah you can't make something that is so complex
the market so simple it's not possible at least an explanation
what happens you can definitely trade it in very simple ways you can trade it in very simple ways
but you know why do people fight fuel the need to give these behaviors false narratives because
initially they're taking trades in areas where they shouldn't be traded pointing their stops in
places they shouldn't be pointed at their stops and then when they get fucked over time and time
again they have to give it a reason for why they're losing the actual reason is you don't know
what the fuck you're doing bro yeah that's true get it
they have no edge
they're seeing these trends
they're applying these tools
that they learn on baby pips and thinking
just because on a historical chart
I can find examples that it worked
that it will mean it will work in the future
that doesn't necessarily mean there's edge
there like I said I can show you
a coin toss chart
and it seems
it seems as if there's trends there
but does that mean the trend will
continue in the future
and then you will be able to exploit in the future
they could entirely separate arguments
or entirely separate questions
again it's a lack of ability to think and stuff
so honestly these people
they hardly know who they are themselves
and like yeah
I just have a huge problem
with fucking shortcuts and idiots
bro yeah
taking the shortcut
you think it's good at the time but it's just not
all right bro
last thing about
that haven't
kind of yet
specifically talk to you about
this is obviously
the origin of the move
the core liquidity
and if we were to zoom out
we would find that
this whole area
is the higher time frame
shelf
what does the shelf hold
of this damn move
what's the shelf holding
so liquid
shit shit
shit sorry sorry sorry
that is it
just to validate you now
I'm going to go out
to the one hour chart
where was there
oh there you go
can you see this was the last main inventory we sold sideways sold sideways this was the huge
sideways before the pop yeah now if you wanted to be massively technical about it on the lower
time frame what you'll see is this push price to new lows shit no no on the lower time frame
you know what this I'm looking sometimes you need that granular view wow yeah so this push price to new
lows, then price broke that last range here.
Yeah, yeah.
That was the technical breaker, but a British midflow.
And then we also broke midflow earlier in the previous day.
Anyway, that's not what I'm talking about.
So you can have huge, huge amounts of cell volume pushing price down here,
sell market order sales.
So they couldn't be in a 500 million market order sell.
Not in one piece.
there was a market order sell here for one client
that was a few million
another market order sell here for another client
that ended up being $200 million
you get it
and over the course of the selling
there was a huge amount of market order sales
but the reason the market order sales
push price down is because there was weak by liquidity
and the reason market order buys
couldn't push price up is because there was huge
market order sell liquidity
limit order sell liquidity
so we're going to know this
in essence then the 500 million market order sells we're not talking about the cell limit limit orders
the 500 million market order cells did not really transact individually with a lot of bi liquidity
because it was all weak yeah meaning the move down is traded thinly yeah but where is the thick
areas of liquidity then in this move if we know it's not on the buy side and we know the market
order cells are pushing to the thin side creating weaknesses and overall the whole the
whole move is weak as well just like these small fractal versions a week the whole version's weak as
well where is the thick liquidity it's in the shelves where's the the shelf at this point here
of the down move um which which part you referring to this move down where's the last shelf
or where is the shelf which is the last base um somewhere like here sorry this down move here
A to B
You're not wrong about that one
But I'm talking about the down move
Price is selling
Picked up
Shifted out
Range drop
Where's the last space
Can you see the right hand of budget
Yeah perfect
And then
Price drops again
We can see all the sell bases
Prices are hardly pulling back
Where's the last base
That yeah
Yeah
Price breaks it
First sign of weakness
But still continues
Because there's too much weakness
In the bids here
Yeah
right the bids are so even though the sellers are showing weakness now there's still some sell liquidity left but the bids are too weak the whole price off and fuel it higher now a cell basehold sell base hold cell base hold it's a factor price run but the real point that I'm getting at here is in this move we've traded thinly on the way down at the end of it this is the real really the only area that can have sell liquidity inside of it or beneath it here once price pushes past
the selling has stopped
to the sell liquidity
is chasing
and pushing
holding price down
where is the real
sell liquidity
you're going to be
if the middle
is thinly traded
at the origin
so when price
goes into bullish
midflow now
why is it that
these highs aren't holding them
we've seen price run out
market order buyers
get stretched out
exhaust
leave behind that
weak thin by liquidity
and light market order
selling pushes price down
why is it then these high retests don't hold
is because this high originally wasn't put in
because there was a one million trillion billion market order
there's limit order cells there
it's not because there was strong sell liquidity holding price down
it was simply because the market order buying
or pay was so so weak and thin
okay right so imagine
there was 10 million here
four million five million there
3 million there
1 million there
Gaps in the middle
3 million there
Market order by
10 million
pushes
Fills Fills Fills Fills
Until there's only
1 million market order
Left
hits 3 million
Mark
Selling it order
Yeah
Do you get it
It's not a huge
amount of sell liquidity
But it still absorbs
That market order buying
Yeah
Do you get it
Leave him behind
To move up left behind
So a bit of weakness at least.
Market orders dried off, left behind a bit of weakness.
Any light market order sell is able to push price down.
Now once price builds back up, you know, because we know by liquidity chasing price,
by the equity builds up, builds up, absorbs any light selling.
We already know there's weak sell liquidity here.
Yeah.
Whenever the market orders come through, it's quite easily going to push through, right?
Whereas, so the point I'm really making here is we already had three million.
weak already
then this test picked up
1 million yeah
because it was only 1 million market order left
at the highs
which made it even weaker
so these mid-flow highs
are not forming of strong
counter liquidity
but they're actually making
the weak liquidity even weaker
by testing them
okay
compare that to
compare that to come back up to
core where there's 1,300 million
price grabs it one time
the same happens here you had a market order long
stretch stretch stretch stretch until there was only one million left to buy
that got filled rapid there was a bit of weakness left behind in this move
so at least it was weak by liquidity thinly distributed by liquidity
any like market order selling pushes price down yeah yeah yeah
price comes back up again what is there a whole bunch of sell liquidity to
hold price down suck up any buying you can suck it up like a vacuum
do you get it so that's the difference
when the high is going to when the retest holds this retest here is because it's a huge huge amount of sell liquidity wanting to transact when price is embellished midflow and it puts in this high it's already hit a weak area and it's made it even weaker now yeah so when the buying comes back up you can get bam all right so the midflow extremes this is the extreme of bearish midflow this is the extreme of bullish midflow this is the extreme of bullish midflow this is the extreme of bullish midflow
we do not expect retests of them.
It's critical you understand that
because it's already weak liquidity.
The extreme is being put in
not because of strong liquidity
on the opposite end,
but because of exhaustion.
Okay.
The market order is exhausting.
You get it?
So hopefully that makes sense.
That you should be able to answer
why, if I'm trying to trade counterflow,
I wouldn't be taking retest, basically.
In that question,
that's going to wrap up
today's session.
If you have any questions, let me know.